Guide to the Gail and Stephen Rudin collection of Simon Lake submarine materials, 1898-1964.
Rudin, Gail and Stephen Rudin collection of Simon Lake submarine materials
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Gail and Stephen Rudin collection of Simon Lake submarine materials, 1898-1964.
6992
Rudin, Stephen,
.5 cubic feet.
Correspondence, printed materials, publications, photographs
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Letters, stock certificates, drawings, photographs, and publications related to Simon Lake's designs for submarines.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Letters, stock certificates, drawings, photographs, and publications related to Simon Lake's designs for submarines.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Rudin, Stephen,; Lake, Simon, 1866-1945.
Subjects:
Submarines (Ships).
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Letters, Manuscripts, and Documents
Series II. Photographs
Series III. Magazines, Reprints, and Pamphlets
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Letters, Manuscripts, and Documents
  - "A Trip to the Submarine Boat Argonaut", October 14, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Typewritten manuscript. Embellished with ink cutaway drawings of the vessel. Apparently presented to Lake after a visit to the Erie Basin.
    Rudin # SL-1
  - Draft contract between Lake and battery manufacturer in Russia, July 8, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Signed by Lake.
    Rudin # SL-2
  - Simon Lake Addressee: Boston Sunday Herald Writer's location: New York, October 2, 1939; TLS; Pages: 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Letter about military submarines and the use of cargo-carrying submarines. Accompanied by a photo of Lake showing what a cargo-carrying submarine might look like.
    Rudin # SL-3
  - Simon Lake Addressee: son-in-law Writer's location: Philadelphia, May 21, 1942; ALS; Pages: 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    States that Lake will be meeting with Mr. (J. Louis) Reynolds on the matter of cargo-carrying submarines.
    Rudin # SL-4
  - Simon Lake Addressee: son-in-law Cecil Ford Writer's location:, n.d.; TLS; Pages: 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Instructions for yard and property maintenance while Lake is away on a trip.
    Rudin # SL-5
  - Simon Lake Addressee: Wife, n.d.; ANS; Pages: 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    "To my wife 'Mocky', with fond recollections of 53 years..." with photo of Lake.
    Rudin # SL-6
  - Simon Lake Addressee: Daughter Writer's location: New York, 1929; ALS; Pages: 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Rudin # SL-7
  - Simon Lake, February 11, 1938; ADS; Pages: 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    On Lakeolith letterhead, transferring ownership of household furniture to a daughter at the family's Milford, Connecticut home. Also signed by son and other daughter.
    Rudin # SL-8
  - Simon Lake Addressee: Elwood Ford, grandson Writer's location: Milford, CT., November 14, 1940; ALS; Pages: 2 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    In pencil, with envelope bearing signature.
    Rudin # SL-9
  - Simon Lake Addressee: Elwood Ford, grandson, June 17, 1944; ALS; Pages: 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    To grandson at an Army Air Corps base in Gulfport, on Lake Submarine Co. letterhead.
    Rudin # SL-10
  - Ford, Elwood Addressee: Mr. and Mrs. Cecil Ford, May 1, 1944; ALS; Pages: 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Includes photo of Ford.
    Rudin # SL-11
  - Simon Lake Addressee: Lawrence Dale Coleman, December 20, 1938; TLS; Pages: 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Asks for names of museums in Venezuela in the event a planned submarine excursion finds materials of interest.
    Rudin # A-137
  - Simon Lake Stock Certificate in Lake Submarine Co., February 19, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Signed twice by Lake. 100 shares.
    Rudin # SL-12
  - Stock certificate for the Lake Sub-Marine Company., May 15, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Signed by Lake. Cancelled.
    Rudin # SL-13
  - Capital stock certificate for five shares in the Lake Sub-Marine Company, made out to J.C. Lake and signed by Simon Lake., January 21, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Rudin # A-133
  - Capital stock certificate for five shares in the Lake Sub-Marine Company, made out to E. Bunge and Co., August 6, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Rudin # A-134
  - Stock certificate for the Lake Torpedo and Boat Company. Rudin # SL-14, August 25, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Invitation to Lake from Theodore Roosevelt for a reception at the White House. Rudin # SL-15, February 18, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Original signed drawing of what appears to be a submarine., June 17 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Rudin # A-135
  - Original signed drawing of Steam Cylinder for Submarine., March 7, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Rudin # A-136
  - "In Defense of the Submarine" manuscript, by Simon Lake., May, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    "In Defense of the Submarine" as well as two other manuscripts, one extolling "unsinkable" ships and the other the virtues of the submarine.
    Rudin # A-138
- Series II: Photographs
  - Photo of Lake (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Signed on verso "Simon Lake- Age 42"
    Rudin # SL-16
  - Photo of Lake in his 60's (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Signed by Lake on verso in pencil "Simon Lake to Ma".
    Rudin # SL-17
  - Original photo of the Argonaut, Lake's first submarine, after being lengthened and made watertight., 1898 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Appears in Lake's 1918 book "The Submarine in War and Peace", pages 182-183.
    Rudin # SL-18
  - Original photo of a model of "The Aluminaut", an aluminum cargo-carrying submarine, with Lake, Reynolds, and staff., ca. 1942 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Rudin # SL-22
  - Lake Torpedo and Boat Co. photo of USS S-49 prior to launch at Bridgeport. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    With Navy history of the submarine.
    Rudin # SL-23
  - USS S-48, December 8, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    With Navy history of the USS S-48 submarine.
    Rudin # SL-24
  - Five Generations Lake reunion., 1935 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Rudin # SL-27
  - Four original photos of "The Protector" (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Rudin # SL-19
  - Original photo of "The Protector" after being renamed "The Osetr" (Folder 1)
    With entire Russian crew, their names penned on lower mount.
    Rudin # SL-20
  - USS S-47 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Rudin # SL-25
- Series III. Magazines, Reprints, and Pamphlets
  - "The Future of the Submarine", printed presentation by Lake to Optimist Club of Philadelphia (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Rudin # SL-28
  - The Lake Periscope, March, April 1920 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Company magazine of Lake Torpedo Boat Co., including visit by Pershing to factory.
    Rudin # SL-32
  - "Sage Submarine Vessels and the Future of the Art", 1907 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Pamphlet by Lake, illustrated.
    Rudin # SL-33
  - "Recovering Natural Products of the Sea", 1920 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Pamphlet, bears the name of Submarine and Exploration Co.
    Rudin # SL-34
  - Pamphlet, "Fortunes Under the Sea", by Simon Lake., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Rudin # SL-35
  - Pamphlet, "The Argonaut: Her Evolution and History", by Simon Lake, July 1900 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Rudin # SL-36
  - Pamphlet, "The Development of the Lake Type Submarine Torpedo Boats". Two copies, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Rudin # SL-37, A-132
  - Pamphlet, "Captain Simon Lake, Inventor of the Submarine, has Perfected Equipment to Salvage Fortunes Now Under the Sea"., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Rudin # SL-38
  - Pamphlet, "Commissioning of United States Ship Simon Lake (AS-33)". Puget Sound Naval Shipyard., November 7, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    48 pages with photo of ship.
    Rudin # SL-39
  - "Modern Submarines in War and Peace", 1918 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Reprint.
    Rudin # SL-40
  - "The Submarine Versus the Submersible", by Simon Lake., May, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Rudin # SL-41
  - Three copies of "Scientific American", 1898, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Article on the Argonaut, other articles by Lake with illustrations.
    Rudin # SL-29-31
  - Illustration from "Recovering Natural Products from the Sea" (Box 3, Folder 4)
SEPARATED MATERIAL
Books on Simon Lake and the Submarine.
Underwater Torpedo Boats: Their Merits and Their Menace, Lake Torpedo Boat Co. Includes content on "The Protector" sold to Russia. Rudin # SL-43.
Ancient and Modern Ships: Part 1, George C.V. Holmes, 1906. Signed by Lake. Rudin # SL-44.
Ancient and Modern Ships: Part II, George C.V. Holmes, 1906. Rudin # SL-45.
The Storage Battery, Augustus Treadwell Jr., 1902. Rudin # SL-46.
Sixty Years' Recollections of Milford, Nathan Stowe, 1917. Signed by Lake. Rudin # SL-47.
A Genealogy of the Lake Family and Submarine. Rudin # SL-48.
The Autobiography of Simon Lake. Rudin # SL-49.